<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="Resolution" id="us/ca/cities/san-diego/council/resolutions/312898">
  <num type="Resolution">312898</num>
  <heading>A Resolution of the Council of the City of San Diego Approving the Reappropriation and Expenditure of Former San Diego Regional Enterprise Zone Program Funds to the Small Business Relief Fund to Address Economic Impacts of the COVID-19 Virus</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-26</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./312898.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://docs.sandiego.gov/council_reso_ordinance/rao2020/R-312898.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-26</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>3/25/0 020 (R-2020-423) REV. COPY RESOLUTION NUMBER R- 312898 DATE OF FINAL PASSAGE MAR 2 6 2020 A RESOLUTION OF THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SAN DIEGO APPROVING THE REAPPROPRIATION AND EXPENDITURE OF FORMER SAN DIEGO REGIONAL ENTERPRISE ZONE PROGRAM FUNDS TO THE SMALL BUSINESS RELIEF FUND TO ADDRESS ECONOMIC IMPACTS OF THE COVID-19 VIRUS. WHEREAS, on February 19, 2020, the County Board of Supervisors ratified a declaration of local health emergency related to a novel coronavirus, the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, on March 4, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom proclaimed a State of Emergency to exist in California as a result of the threat of the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, Mayor Kevin Faulconer proclaimed the existence of a local emergency in the City of San Diego (City) as a result of the COVID-19 virus, which was ratified by the Council of the City of San Diego (Council) on March 17, 2020; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, the County of San Diego issued an order from the Public Health Officer requiring, among other things, all bars, adult entertainment establishments, and other business establishments in the County that serve alcohol and do not serve food to close, and requiring all restaurants to close on-site dining; and WHEREAS, on March 16, 2020, the Mayor issued Executive Order No. 2020-1 prohibiting, among other things, public gatherings of 50 or more people in a single room, closing all bars, adult entertainment establishments, and nightclubs in the City, and prohibiting restaurants from serving food and beverage for consumption on premises; and WHEREAS, on March 19, 2020, the Governor issued Executive Order N-33-20, ordering all residents of the State of California to stay home or at their place of residence in accordance with the current State public health directives; and PAGE 1 OF 4- (R-2020-423) REV. COPY WHEREAS, in order to alleviate the economic impacts of the COVID-19 virus, the City seeks to implement various programs to encourage economic relief and stimulus, and reduce financial hardship for impacted businesses in the City, including a grant and loan program for small businesses called the "Small Business Relief Fund;" and WHEREAS, the City previously received funds as the administrator of the former San Diego Regional Enterprise Zone (SDREZ Funds), and allocated, appropriated, and expended a portion of the SDREZ Funds to certain contracts and programs that support new and existing economic and workforce development opportunities; and WHEREAS, the SDREZ Funds can be used to support the City's economic and workforce development initiatives, including strategic opportunities with long-term economic growth benefit potential, and to complement regional economic development goals of the City's Strategic Framework Plan and Economic Development Strategy; and WHEREAS, the City desires to allocate certain unexpended SDREZ Funds to the Small Business Relief Fund to support businesses' ability to sustain operations, retain employees, address unforeseen changes to supply and demand, and alleviate immediate and long-term economic impacts related to the COVID-19 virus; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED, by the Council of the City of San Diego as follows: 1. The Chief Financial Officer is authorized to appropriate SDREZ Funds in Economic &amp; Workforce Development Fund No. 200736 to the Small Business Relief Fund as follows: $400,000 reappropriated from the Placemaking Revolving Loan Fund; and $150,000 from the Activation Grants Program. -PAGE 2 OF 4- (R-2020-423) REV. COPY 2. The Chief Financial Officer is authorized to appropriate and expend an amount not to exceed $550,000 from Fund No. 200736 for any contracts entered as part of the City's Small Business Relief Fund. 3 . The Mayor, or designee, is authorized to negotiate and enter into agreements, execute any and all documents, and take all other necessary actions necessary or appropriate to implement this Resolution. 4. All small business relief fund applications must include a statement of financial hardship in connection with COVID-19 as well as meet all the eligibility requirements set by the Economic Development Department in order to receive funds. Financial hardship shall mean a decrease in business income, reduction in labor force is imminent, reduction in consumer demand, production and/or ability to fulfill product and service orders. APPROVED: MARA W. ELLIOTT, City Attorney By Daphne Z. Skogen Deputy City Attorney DZS:soc 03/20/2020 03/25/2020 REV. COPY Or.Dept: EconDev Doc. No.: 2356655 -PAGE 3 OF 4- (R-2020-423) REV. COPY I certify that the foregging Resolution was passed by the Council of the City of San Diego, at this meeting of ELIZABETH S. MALAND City Clerk By Connie Patterson Deputy City Clerk Approved: 3/ 26 / 2020 (date) Then ley KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor Vetoed: (date) KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor PAGE 4 OF 4- Passed by the Council of The City of San Diego on MAR 2 5 2020 by the following vote: Councilmembers Yeas Nays Not Present Recused Barbara Bry Jennifer Campbell Chris Ward Monica Montgomery Mark Kersey Chris Cate Scott Sherman Vivian Moreno Georgette Gomez 0OOOOOOOC Date of final passage MAR 2 6 2020 (Please note: When a resolution is approved/unsigned by the Mayor, the date of final passage is the date the approved/unsigned resolution was returned to the Office of the City Clerk.) KEVIN L. FAULCONER AUTHENTICATED BY: Mayor of The City of San Diego, California. ELIZABETH S, MALAND (Seal) City Clerk of The City of San Diego, California. By Connie Patton,Deputy Office of the City Clerk, San Diego, California Resolution Number R- 312898</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
