<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="Resolution" id="us/ca/cities/san-diego/council/resolutions/312895">
  <num type="Resolution">312895</num>
  <heading>A Resolution of the Council of the City of San Diego Ratifying the Mayor’s March 12, 2020 Proclamation of a Local Emergency Regarding the Coronavirus COVID-19 Outbreak.</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-12</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./312895.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://docs.sandiego.gov/council_reso_ordinance/rao2020/R-312895.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-17</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>ITEM # 600 TUESDAY, March 17, 2010 (R-2020-401) RESOLUTION NUMBER R-_ 312895 DATE OF FINAL PASSAGE MAR 1 7 2020 A RESOLUTION OF THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SAN DIEGO RATIFYING THE MAYOR'S MARCH 12, 2020 PROCLAMATION OF A LOCAL EMERGENCY REGARDING THE CORONAVIRUS COVID-19 OUTBREAK. WHEREAS, a novel coronavirus, COVID-19, causes infectious disease and was first detected in December 2019; and WHEREAS, COVID-19 virus symptoms include fever, cough, and shortness of breath; outcomes have ranged from mild to severe illness, and in some cases death; and WHEREAS, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention considers the virus to be a very serious public health threat; and WHEREAS, on January 30, 2020, the World Health Organization declared the outbreak a "public health emergency of international concern;" and WHEREAS, on January 31, 2020, United States Health and Human Services Secretary Alex M. Azar II declared a public health emergency for the United States to aid the nation's healthcare community in responding to COVID-19; and WHEREAS, as of February 14, 2020, there were two confirmed cases of COVID-19 in San Diego County and the San Diego County Public Health Officer has determined that due to the large population and geographic location of San Diego County, combined with the worldwide spread of COVID-19, there is a potential threat of introduction of COVID-19 in San Diego County and declared a Local Health Emergency; and WHEREAS, on February 19, 2020, the County Board of Supervisors ratified the Declaration of Local Health Emergency; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, pursuant to San Diego Municipal Code -PAGE 1 OF 4- (R-2020-401) section 51.0105(a)(1), the Mayor proclaimed the existence of a local emergency as a result of the coronavirus COVID-19 outbreak; and WHEREAS, San Diego Municipal Code section 51.0105(a)(1) requires that the City Council ratify the proclamation within seven days thereafter or the proclamation shall have no further force or effect; and WHEREAS, the City Council is committed to working with the Mayor to develop recommendations for emergency and mutual aid plans and agreements and such ordinances, resolutions, rules, and regulations necessary to implement such plans and agreements; and WHEREAS, conditions of disaster or extreme peril to the safety of persons and property continue to directly affect the safety of persons and property within the City; and WHEREAS, California Government Code section 8630 authorizes local governing bodies to proclaim local emergencies when such events occur as are defined by California Government Code section 8558(c), provided further by section 8630 that the local governing body must review the state of emergency at least every thirty days until the emergency is declared to be terminated and shall proclaim the termination of the local emergency at the earliest possible date that conditions warrant; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED, by the Council of the City of San Diego, that pursuant to California Government Code section 8630, a state of local emergency due to the continued threat of spread of the novel coronavirus, Covid-19, is declared to exist in the City of San Diego, and has existed since February 14, 2020, throughout the City, and that proclamation of the state of emergency by the Mayor on March 12, 2020 is hereby ratified. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the Council hereby ratifies and approves, in accordance with the police powers vested in City officials under the Constitution of the State of -PAGE 2 OF 4- (R-2020-401) California, the City Charter, and the laws of this State including the aforementioned Government Code provisions, all orders and regulations promulgated, issued and carried out by City officers and City officials from February 14, 2020, until the passage of this resolution, which are and were necessary to provide for the protection of life and property. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that during the existence of this local emergency, the powers, functions and duties of the Mayor of this City shall be those prescribed by State law and the Charter, ordinances, resolutions and approved plans of the City of San Diego in order to mitigate the effects of this local emergency, including the receipt, processing, and coordination of all inquiries and requirements necessary to obtain available state and federal assistance. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the state of local emergency shall be deemed to continue until its termination is proclaimed by the City Council. APPROVED: MARA W. ELLIOTT, City Attorney By Prescilla Dugard Senior Chief Deputy City Attorney PMD:jvg 03/10/20 Or.Dept: Mayor CC No. N/A Doc. No.: 2349108 -PAGE 3 OF 4- (R-2020-401) I certify that the foregoing Resolution was passed by the Council of the City of San Diego, at this meeting of MAR 1 7 2020 ELIZABETH SAMALAND City Clerk By Approved: 3/17 / 20 T(date KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor Vetoed: (date) KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor -PAGE 4 OF 4- Passed by the Council of The City of San Diego on_ MAR 1 7 2020 by the following vote: Councilmembers Yeas Nays Not Present Recused Barbara Bry Jennifer Campbell Chris Ward Monica Montgomery Mark Kersey Chris Cate Scott Sherman Vivian Moreno Georgette Gomez 000000000 Date of final passage MAR 1 7 2020 (Please note: When a resolution is approved by the Mayor, the date of final passage is the date the approved resolution was returned to the Office of the City Clerk.) KEVIN L. FAULCONER AUTHENTICATED BY: Mayor of The City of San Diego, California. ELIZABETH S. MALAND (Seal) City Clerk of The City of San Diego, California. Deputy Office of the City Clerk, San Diego, California Resolution Number R- 312895</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
