<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="Resolution" id="us/ca/cities/san-diego/council/resolutions/312897">
  <num type="Resolution">312897</num>
  <heading>A Resolution of the Council of the City of San Diego Adopting Comprehensive Actions to Address Economic and Social Impacts Caused by the State and Local Health Emergency Related to the Novel Coronavirus, COVID-19</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-04-02</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./312897.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://docs.sandiego.gov/council_reso_ordinance/rao2020/R-312897.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-04-02</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>Item #601 3/17 / 2020 B (R-2020-416) RESOLUTION NUMBER R- 312897 DATE OF FINAL PASSAGE APR 0 2 2020 A RESOLUTION OF THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SAN DIEGO ADOPTING COMPREHENSIVE ACTIONS TO ADDRESS ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL IMPACTS CAUSED BY THE STATE AND LOCAL HEALTH EMERGENCY RELATED TO THE NOVEL CORONAVIRUS, COVID-19. WHEREAS, a novel coronavirus, COVID-19, causes infectious disease and was first detected in December 2019; and WHEREAS, COVID-19 virus symptoms include fever, cough, and shortness of breath; outcomes have ranged from mild to severe illness, and in some cases death; and WHEREAS, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention considers the virus to be a very serious public health threat; and WHEREAS, on February 19, 2020, the County Board of Supervisors ratified a declaration of local health emergency related to the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, on March 4, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom proclaimed a State of Emergency to exist in California as a result of the threat of the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, Mayor Kevin Faulconer proclaimed the existence of a local emergency in the City of San Diego as a result of the COVID-19 virus, which was ratified by the Council of the City of San Diego on March 17, 2020; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, the County of San Diego (County) issued an order from the Public Health Officer requiring, among other things, all bars, adult entertainment establishments, and other business establishments in the County that serve alcohol and do not serve food to close, and requiring all restaurants to close on-site dining; and -PAGE 1 OF 5- (R-2020-416) WHEREAS, on March 16, 2020, the Mayor issued Executive Order No. 2020-1 prohibiting, among other things, public gatherings of 50 or more people in a single room, closing all bars, adult entertainment establishments, and nightclubs in the City, and prohibiting restaurants from serving food and beverage for consumption on premises; and WHEREAS, the Council desires to call on federal, state, and local government agencies and utilities to take action to alleviate the economic and social impacts of actions taken to address the local health emergency related to the COVID-19 virus; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED, by the Council of the City of San Diego, that the Council requests the Congressional delegation and Federal Administration, to the extent of their authority under the law, to direct the Department of Homeland Security to suspend immigration enforcement operations, including interior checkpoints in sensitive locations including hospitals, clinics, and other healthcare facilities. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the Council requests the San Diego Housing Commission (Housing Commission) to the extent of its authority under the law, to evaluate and present proposals to the Council or the Housing Authority of the City of San Diego to implement a temporary moratorium on evictions and mortgage foreclosures for property owned by the Housing Authority or Housing Commission due to non-payment of rent or mortgages resulting from a loss in wages caused by the outbreak of the COVID-19 virus. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the Council requests the San Diego Superior Court, to the extent of its authority under the law, to temporarily suspend all pending residential eviction cases and reject new filings of residential eviction cases during the pendency of the state of emergency related to the outbreak of the COVID-19 virus. -PAGE 2 OF 5- (R-2020-416) BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the Council requests the San Diego County Sheriff, to the extent of his authority under the law, to suspend service of unlawful detainer actions and enforcement of evictions within the City of San Diego due to non-payment of rent resulting from a loss of wages caused by the outbreak of the COVID-19 virus. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that the Council requests the Mayor take the following actions, to the extent of his authority under the law: 1. Work with San Diego Gas &amp; Electric (SDG&amp;E) and other utility providers to evaluate potential relief from late fees and utility shut-offs due to non-payment resulting from a loss of wages caused by the outbreak of the COVID-19 virus and request SDG&amp;E consider using its Tier 1 rates during daytime hours to alleviate the potentially significant economic impact that higher rate energy tiers could have on City residents working from home; 2. Evaluate temporary relief funding for workers within the City who were laid off or furloughed as a result of the outbreak of the COVID-19 virus to help those workers pay rent and/or utility bills; 3. Evaluate and report to Council on a strategy with potential options to work with banks and lenders to halt mortgage payments or foreclosures for individuals and landlords who have suffered severe loss of wages and income due to the outbreak of the COVID-19 virus; 4. Temporarily prioritize requests for emergency funding and support from the state and federal governments as the overriding number one Citywide priority; 5. Enforce the Earned Sick Leave and Minimum Wage Ordinance, San Diego Municipal Code sections 39.0101 through 39.0116; PAGE 3 OF 5- (R-2020-416) 6. Evaluate and report to Council on delaying collection and enforcement of the City's Business Tax Certificate fees; 7. Evaluate and report to Council on a strategy to implement a temporary moratorium on the Vehicle Habitation Ordinance, San Diego Municipal Code section 86.0137(f) and the 72-Hour Parking Ordinance, San Diego Municipal Code section 86.0118 for the duration of the declared local emergency related to the continued threat of spread of the COVID-19 virus; and 8. Work with the hotel association, labor partners, and homeless service providers to open hotel rooms that include provider services to unsheltered individuals and families. APPROVED: MARA W. ELLIOTT, City Attorney By Priscilla Duggers for . Heather M. Ferbert Deputy City Attorney HMF:soc 03/18/2020 Or.Dept: Council President's Office Doc. No.: 2353509 PAGE 4 OF 5- (R-2020-416) I certify that the foregoing Resolution was passed by the Council of the City of San Diego, at this meeting of. MAR. 1 7 2020 ELIZABETH $. MALAND City Clerk By Deputy City Clerk Approved: (date) KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor Vetoed: (date) KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor (Note: This resolution was returned unsigned by the Mayor's Office to the Office of the City Clerk on April 2, 2020. Pursuant to the San Diego Charter Section 295(a) (2), the Mayor has 10 business days from the date the resolution was transmitted to sign or veto the resolution, said deadline being close of businessApril 2, 2020. Therefore the date of expiration of that time shall be deemed the date of its final passage.) -PAGE 5 OF 5- Passed by the Council of The City of San Diego on MAR 1 7 2020 , by the following vote: Councilmembers Yeas Nays Not Present Recused Barbara Bry Jennifer Campbell Chris Ward Monica Montgomery Mark Kersey Chris Cate Scott Sherman Vivian Moreno Georgette Gomez 000 0 0 0 0OO Date of final passage APR 0 2 2020 (Please note: When a resolution is approved by the Mayor, the date of final passage is the date the approved resolution was returned to the Office of the City Clerk.) KEVIN L. FAULCONER AUTHENTICATED BY: Mayor of The City of San Diego, California. ELIZABETH S. MALAND (Seal) City Clerk of The City of San Diego, California. By IM . Deputy Office of the City Clerk, San Diego, California Resolution Number R- 312897</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
