<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" prefix="Resolution" id="us/ca/cities/san-diego/council/resolutions/312899">
  <num type="Resolution">312899</num>
  <heading>A Resolution of the Council of the City of San Diego Approving the Allocation of Community Development Block Grant Fiscal Year 2019 and Fiscal Year 2020 Reprogrammed Funds to the Small Business Relief Fund and Authorizing Related Actions to Appropriate and Expend These Funds</heading>
  <heading type="oll"/>
  <meta>
    <status>Adopted</status>
    <effective>2020-03-26</effective>
    <expiration/>
    <link type="pdf" url="./312899.pdf"/>
    <link type="lims" url="https://docs.sandiego.gov/council_reso_ordinance/rao2020/R-312899.pdf"/>
    <history>
      <introduced/>
      <created>2020-03-26</created>
    </history>
    <search-text>3/25/2020 Hem 401/8 (R-2020-424 REV.) RESOLUTION NUMBER R-_31289 9 DATE OF FINAL PASSAGE MAR 2 6 2020 A RESOLUTION OF THE COUNCIL OF THE CITY OF SAN DIEGO APPROVING THE ALLOCATION OF COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT BLOCK GRANT FISCAL YEAR 2019 AND FISCAL YEAR 2020 REPROGRAMMED FUNDS TO THE SMALL BUSINESS RELIEF FUND AND AUTHORIZING RELATED ACTIONS TO APPROPRIATE AND EXPEND THESE FUNDS. WHEREAS, on February 19, 2020, the County Board of Supervisors ratified a declaration of local health emergency related to a novel coronavirus, the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, on March 4, 2020, Governor Gavin Newsom proclaimed a State of Emergency to exist in California as a result of the threat of the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, Mayor Kevin Faulconer proclaimed the existence of a local emergency in the City of San Diego as a result of the COVID-19 virus, which was ratified by the Council of the City of San Diego (Council) on March 17, 2020; and WHEREAS, on March 12, 2020, the County of San Diego issued an order from the Public Health Officer requiring, among other things, all bars, adult entertainment establishments, and other business establishments in the County that serve alcohol and do not serve food to close, and requiring all restaurants to close on-site dining; and WHEREAS, on March 16, 2020, the Mayor issued Executive Order No. 2020-1 prohibiting, among other things, public gatherings of 50 or more people in a single room, closing all bars, adult entertainment establishments, and nightclubs in the City of San Diego, and prohibiting restaurants from serving food and beverage for consumption on premises; and PAGE 1 OF 5- (R-2020-424 REV.) WHEREAS, on March 19, 2020, the Governor issued Executive Order N-33-20, ordering all residents of the State of California to stay home or at their place of residence in accordance with the current State public health directives; and WHEREAS, in order to alleviate the economic impacts of the COVID-19 virus, the City seeks to implement various programs to encourage economic relief and stimulus, and reduce financial hardship for impacted businesses in the City of San Diego, including a grant and loan program for small businesses called the "Small Business Relief Fund;" and WHEREAS, the City is an entitlement jurisdiction that annually receives federal funds from the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) for the Community Development Block Grant (CDBG) Program; and WHEREAS, the City allocated CDBG funds in accordance with the City's Fiscal Year 2015-2019 Consolidated Plan (FY 15-19 Consolidated Plan), adopted on April 30, 2014 by San Diego Resolution No. R-308904 and the Fiscal Year 2019 Annual Action Plan (FY19 Action Plan), adopted on April 23, 2018 by San Diego Resolution No. R-311700; and WHEREAS, the City allocated CDBG funds in accordance with the City's Fiscal Year 2020-2024 Consolidated Plan (FY20-24 Consolidated Plan) and the Fiscal Year 2020 Annual Action Plan (FY20 Action Plan), adopted on April 26, 2019 by San Diego Resolution No. R- 312442; and WHEREAS, unexpended CDBG funds allocated to the Small Business Revolving Loan Fund for Fiscal Year 2019 and to the Neighborhood Business Improvement Program for Fiscal Year 2020 are available and recommended by City staff for reprogramming; and WHEREAS, the City's FY20-24 Consolidated Plan includes economic resiliency as a guiding strategy for all investments, which is defined by the ability to recover quickly from an PAGE 2 OF 5- (R-2020-424 REV.) economic shock, the ability to withstand a shock, and the ability to avoid the shock altogether; and WHEREAS, the Small Business Relief Fund is designed to alleviate the existing conditions and economic impacts related to the COVID-19 virus; and WHEREAS, in accordance with the guiding strategy in the FY20-24 Consolidated Plan, the City seeks to reprogram CDBG funds to the Small Business Relief Fund; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED, by the Council of the City of San Diego as follows: 1 . The Chief Financial Officer is authorized to reallocate $887,285.36 in FY 2019 CDBG Program, Fund 600000, Grant 1000003-2019 to FY 2020 CDBG Program, Fund 600000, Grant 1000003-2020, previously allocated from the Small Business Revolving Loan Fund to the Small Business Relief Fund. 2. The Chief Financial Officer is authorized to appropriate and expend a total of $887,285.36 in FY 2020 CDBG Program, Fund 600000, Grant 1000003-2020 for projects in connection with the Small Business Relief Fund. 3. The Chief Financial Officer is authorized to reallocate $2,500,000 in FY 2020 CDBG Program, Fund 600000, Grant 1000003-2020 previously allocated from the Neighborhood Business Improvement Program to the Small Business Relief Fund. 4. The Chief Financial Officer is authorized to appropriate and expend a total of $2,500,000 in FY 2020 CDBG Program, Fund 600000, Grant 1000003-2020 for projects in connection with the Small Business Relief Fund. 5. The allocation of reprogrammed CDBG funds, is approved, contingent upon the Chief Financial Officer certifying that CDBG funds are available. -PAGE 3 OF 5- (R-2020-424 REV.) 6. The Mayor, or designce, is authorized to amend the FY15-19 Consolidated Plan. FY19 Action Plan and FY20 Action Plan, if necessary or required by HUD. 7. The Mayor, or designee, is authorized to negotiate and enter into agreements, execute any and all documents, and take all other actions necessary or appropriate to implement this Resolution. 8. All small business relief fund applications must include a statement of financial hardship in connection with COVID-19 as well as meet all the eligibility requirements set by the Economic Development Department in order to receive funds. Financial hardship shall mean a decrease in business income, an imminent reduction in labor force, reduction in consumer demand, production and/or ability to fulfill product and service orders. APPROVED: MARA W. ELLIOTT, City Attorney By Marguerite E. Middaugh Deputy City Attorney MEM:jdf 03/19/2020 03/25/2020 REV. Or.Dept: Economic Dev't Doc. No.: 2357258_2 -PAGE 4 OF 5- (R-2020-424 REV.) I certify that the foregoing Resolution was passed by the Council of the City of San Diego, at this meeting of_ MAR 2 5 2020 ELIZABETH S. MALAND City Clerk By Connie Patterson Deputy City Clerk Approved: 3/ 26 / 2020 (date) KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor Vetoed: (date) KEVIN L. FAULCONER, Mayor -PAGE 5 OF 5- Passed by the Council of The City of San Diego on_ MAR 2 5 2020 by the following vote: Councilmembers Yeas Nays Not Present Recused Barbara Bry Jennifer Campbell Chris Ward Monica Montgomery Mark Kersey Chris Cate Scott Sherman Vivian Moreno Georgette Gomez Date of final passage MAR 2 6 2020 (Please note: When a resolution is approved/unsigned by the Mayor, the date of final passage is the date the approved/unsigned resolution was returned to the Office of the City Clerk.) KEVIN L. FAULCONER AUTHENTICATED BY: Mayor of The City of San Diego, California. ELIZABETH S. MALAND (Seal) City Clerk of The City of San Diego, California. By Connie Pastries Deputy Office of the City Clerk, San Diego, California Resolution Number R- 312899</search-text>
  </meta>
</document>
